Inventory of the George Herbert Ryden papers
Hoover Institution Archives
George Herbert Ryden papers
1915-1941
2010C51
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, reports, personal documents, photographs, and memorabilia, relating to relief activities in the Crimea during the Russian Civil War. Includes correspondence with Grand Duchess Ol'ga Aleksandrovna.
Ryden, George Herbert, 1884-1941
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2010.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
George H. Ryden (1884-1941) was an American National Red Cross worker in Russia from 1918 to 1920. A native of Kansas City, he interrupted his academic career to serve with the American Expeditionary Forces in Italy during World War I, was with the Red Cross in the southern Russian city of Novorossisk in 1920, seeking to aid refugees during the civil war that followed the Russian Revolution. While there, he played a key role in helping the family of Grand Duchess Olga Alexandrovna, the sister of the recently murdered Czar Nicholas II, escape to Turkey and subsequently to Europe. Ryden, a historian, later became the state archivist of Delaware.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, reports, personal documents, photographs, and memorabilia, relating to Red Cross relief activities in the Crimea during the Russian Civil War. Includes correspondence with Grand Duchess Ol'ga Aleksandrovna.
The twenty-three letters and postcards from the Grand Duchess were written from Denmark between 1923 and 1929. Several of these postcards contain reproductions of her paintings, which Ryden helped sell in the United States during the 1920s and 1930s.
In addition to the correspondence with Olga Alexandrovna, Ryden's papers contain a variety of documents pertaining to Red Cross operations in the Crimea and southern Russia, including correspondence, reports of visits to orphanages and hospitals, and financial records. Ryden and his colleagues received a number of honors from White Russian Army commanders, and his papers contain documents concerning honors and medals that he and his colleagues were awarded, including Ryden's honorary membership in the Kuban Cossacks, and medals that were bestowed on him by Generals Denikin and Wrangel. Following his service with the Red Cross, Ryden visited Denmark in 1921 to meet once again with Olga Alexandrovna, as well as with her mother, the empress dowager Mariia Feodorovna, who expressed her gratitude to Ryden with an inscribed photograph that read "In gratitude for what you did for my daughter," and signed simply "Marie."
Ryden's academic career and interest in history are also represented in correspondence with the acadmic insitutions that he attended, student transcripts, and certificates of membership from various state historical societies.
American National Red Cross.; Ol'ga Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess of Russia, 1882-1960.; International relief.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Civilian relief.
- Academic Career File, 1915-1924
  - Correspondence, 1915-1924 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Biographical File, 1918-1957, undated
  - Business Cards, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - American Expeditionary Forces identification card, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Delaware Historical Markers Commission membership certificate, 1923, 1931 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Pennsylvania Historical Society membership certificate, 1924 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Passports, 1924, 1933 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1938-1957 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Kansas City Southern Railway Co. letter of recommendation, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 46)
  - "Honorary Cossack," certification, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 5)
- YMCA Italy File, 1918
  - Letters of introduction, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Ol'ga Alexandrovna Materials, 1923-2008
  - Correspondence, 1923-1929 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Correspondence, 1923-1941, 1960 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Postcards with artwork, 1929-1932 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1957-2008 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Receipts for sale of paintings, 1925-1930 (Box-folder 1: 13)
- Correspondence, 1919-1941
  - "May", 1941 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - General Boris Shoulgin, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - A. Staritzky (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Baroness Olga Wrangel, 1920, 1924 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Russian Embassy in Paris, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Russian Plenipotentiary, Constantinople, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 19)
- American Red Cross Materials, 1919-1921, undated
  - Correspondence, 1919-1922
    - Max Ferrand, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 24)
    - Burris Jenkins, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 25)
    - Johnson, 1922 (Box-folder 1: 44)
    - Leonid Lenko-Popovsky, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 22)
    - Horace Morrison, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 26)
    - R. E. Olds, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 27)
    - Charles Smith, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 29)
    - Leon K. Wiese, 1922 (Box-folder 1: 43)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 28)
    - Insurance Policies, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 30)
    - Personal Finances, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 31)
    - Social Initiatives, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 32)
    - Russian Red Cross, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 37)
    - 1920 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Decorations Awarded to Staff by Russian Military, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - "An Account of the Evacuation of Crimea," Leon K. Wiese, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - "An Account of the Evacuation of Crimea," G. H. Ryden, 1921 (Box-folder 1: 42)
  - Letters of Introduction, undated (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - Memorandum, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 36)
  - "An Account of General Denikine's Speech at Ekaterinodar", 1920 (Box-folder 1: 38)
  - "General Holman's Proclamation to all the Athamen of Territories, Districts, and Villages and to all Cossacks of the Kuban and Don", 1920 (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - Reports on meetings with Russian officials, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 40)
  - Reports on visits to hospitals and orphanages, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 41)
  - Notebook, undated (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - Blank stationary, undated (Box-folder 2: 6)
- Russian Red Cross Materials, 1920
  - Letters of introduction, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Letter in recognition of Ryden's service, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 35)
- Delaware Materials, 1938-1941
  - Swedish history materials, 1938, 1941 (Box-folder 1: 45)
- Russian Army Materials, 1919
  - Letter of introduction, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 47)
- Photographs, undated
  - Portraits of Ryden, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Portraits of General Baron Wrangel and Maria Feodorovna, undated (Box-folder 2: 10)
- Appointments Committee for Russian Scientific and Literary Men report, 1921 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- "Significance of Crimea," speech notes, 1921 (Box-folder 2: 2)
- "Panorama of Sebastopol," report, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Business cards, ephemera, undated (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Medals, undated (Box-folder 2: 11)